[music]
>> Here in the heart of the
Oxfordshire countryside
there is a world heritage site, one of
Europe's most stunning buildings.
It's the only non-royal, non-episcopal
building in England to be called a
palace. And its name is justified. Look
at that. Blenheim Palace, one of the
most stunning sites anywhere in the UK.
It was built by John Churchill, the
first Duke of Marlborough, in a sort of
celebration for the stunning series of
victories he won over Louis the XIV's
France.
It's
>> [music]
>> a brilliant surviving example of English
Baroque architecture.
And it's been home to the same family,
the Churchill family, for 300 years
since their ancestor built it. It's also
the birthplace of one of
John Churchill's more famous, more
remarkable descendants,
Winston.
>> [music]
>> In this film, I'm going to take you on
an exclusive tour of this magnificent
building.
The spectacular architecture
and the sumptuous interiors.
We'll see the treasures of the private
archive
and learn more about Blenheim's most
famous son.
But our tour starts with the woman
without whom
there would be no Blenheim Palace at
all.
>> Queen Anne is central to this property
and to this family. It was under her
auspices, as it says, that John
Churchill, Duke of Marlborough, won all
these great victories. His wife was a
favorite of hers. Well, they had a
tempestuous relationship, but at times
she was a favorite. Um and it was
because of his wife's relationship that
he was able to cement himself in control
of her armies. And this property is the
result. And this is one of the most
magnificent rooms. It was a gallery. It
was for paintings you take your walks in
here on rainy days and look up at all
the paintings on the wall. Today you've
got various relatives, various royal
family members up there. But it's also a
library now, 10,000 volumes. And I would
just love
to come in here and explore all these
volumes.
As long as someone didn't start playing
the organ at the end.
Not quite sure what that's doing in a
library.
>> [music]
[music]
>> The interior of the palace is just
extraordinarily opulent. It is literally
palatial. I mean, just look at this room
here.
Beautiful 24-karat gold leaf ceiling.
And the paintings on the walls of
members of the Churchill
Spencer-Churchill family
uh through the ages, painted by some of
the finest artists in in British life.
Like Reynolds. Behind me here, this is
an important one. We've got Sarah
Churchill. She's the reason we're all
here. She was the first Duchess. She was
the uh confidant of Queen Anne. She She
sort of shored up
John Churchill's position at court while
he was overseas fighting uh for Queen
and country. They were a the premier
political power couple of late Stuart
England. Uh and she he's up there in his
military uniform. And the combination of
his military skill and her
political nous at court uh ensured the
birth of this dynasty that would go on
for generations.
This room's great cuz this room is all
about the first Duke. There he is on the
wall there. And now we explore the first
Duke as a great military commander,
arguably Britain's greatest ever
general. These are huge tapestries that
he had commissioned.
They were made in that the European
hotspot for for tapestries and
needlework in the low countries around
Brussels, what we now think of as
Belgium. And they were very very
accurate. He was determined that they
would accurately reflect his campaigns.
So the faces and the individuals
portrayed are as they were on the
battlefield. Is this the most famous of
the vast tapestries?
This is the Battle of Blenheim. Blenheim
was his most famous victory, hence
Blenheim Palace. It's a place in
southern Germany. It's a
hugely remote. All the great British
victories in history, if you think about
it, they're all quite near the coast.
The British don't tend to like going too
far away from their their naval
uh lifeline. But Marlborough led his men
deep into the heart of Germany and he
fought a big coalition battle against
the French. Here we see his allies.
Those are all individual allied
commanders, Germans, people from the low
countries, elsewhere. And then there's
Blenheim. There's the Danube running
through the valley, the church steeple
uh famous on the battlefield as a
landmark.
Uh and then we have the surrender of the
French commander, the French marshal.
The French always wore white,
surrendering uh
Marlborough receiving the surrender,
holding his field marshal's baton. And
look down here in the corner. I love
this. I love the detail of these early
18th century uniforms. In its own right,
this is a great historical resource. And
he is holding a captured standard
belonging to Louis XIV. You can see the
fleur-de-lis, the white standard of the
of the French royal army. So this is a a
gigantic celebration of the apotheosis
of Marlborough's career. And it hangs
here in the house that he built um with
the spoils of that victory.
This is just a glorious room. There's
nothing quite like it. It's the saloon.
It's now the dining room where they eat.
It's the sort of main reception room.
It's painted the murals on every wall
and ceiling painted showing the peoples
of the world at peace after the war of
Spanish Succession. It's a giant global
war that was fighting in India, North
America, and Europe uh fighting all over
the place to to restrain Louis XIV.
Louis XIV wanted to put his grandson on
the throne of Spain, the vacant throne
of Spain. So, he'd been frustrated in
that aim, and now the peoples of the
world could live in harmony thank you to
the Duke of Marlborough and his
victories. And remarkably,
the artist has included himself. He's
done a selfie. There he is. His name is
Louis Laguerre. Even more bizarrely,
he's a Frenchman. His name means war,
and he's painted this gigantic
celebration of peace. And finally, most
strangely of all, he's actually Louis
XIV's godson. Now, whether that's
uh shows how enlightened the first Duke
was bringing his former enemies into
this celebration of peace,
I don't know. It could be that he was
just rubbing their nose in it.
>> [music]
>> It's one of my favorite objects in this
palace. One of my In fact, it's one of
my favorite objects of all time. I love
this. This is the Blenheim Dispatch.
Now, it was written by the first Duke uh
on the battlefield at Blenheim in a
hurry. Look at it. You can see how how
scruffy his writing is. And we know it
was in a hurry particularly because it
was written on the back of a bill from a
tavern for the previous night's meal.
You can see that
it's in French. Plu de vin, a bit of
meat. Chandelle, couple of candles.
Uh de pain, some bread. So, someone's
given him this scrap of paper and he's
written in a rushed way to say look,
August the 13th.
Um 1704. I have not time to say more but
beg you will give my duty to the Queen
and let her know that the army has had a
glorious victory.
Marshall Tallard and two other generals
are in my coach and I'm following up the
rest. I either French is sitting in his
coach. That is a pretty comprehensive
victory. I just love the fact that news
of such strategic importance was
delivered on the back of a a bar bill.
This victory that he was so proud of uh
was a very important victory. It proved
decisive and it was the reason that
Queen Anne, his sovereign, gave him this
land that had been royal hunting land
for centuries and the money to build
this gigantic palace. In return, she
asked simply for one thing. That every
year a standard be delivered to her and
her successors with the French
fleur-de-lis on it. And to this day, for
the last 300 years, the Dukes of
Marlborough every single year have been
delivering that to Windsor at the
appointed time. George VI in 1946 gave
one of the standards back so it could be
displayed here at Blenheim so visitors
would understand the process.
And I hope they've got their calendar
alerts set to annual because if the
family do ever forget
the Queen's having this place back.
The building of Blenheim was far from
smooth. Construction began in 1705
but a few years later the Queen and the
Duchess fell out.
The Marlboroughs had to flee into exile
and work on the palace stopped.
It wasn't finished until the 1730s
but the result was magnificent.
It's just built on such a grand scale.
It's gigantic. In fact, it feels more
like a an Oxford college and well, it's
partly because it's made from the same
beautiful golden stone of the Cotswolds.
And the architects who worked on it are
some of the foremost architects in
British history.
Vanbrugh, led, ably assisted by
Hawksmoor.
The private The current Duke's family,
direct descendant of
uh that first Duke, live in that
apartment over there.
And taken as a whole, it is still the
biggest private [music] residence
in the country.
Well, all that gold leaf and those
paintings are fine as far as they go,
but everyone knows Well, history geeks
like me know, the real action is in the
archives. That's where the treasures
are. And I'm off now to meet Dr. Alexa
Frost, and she's going to show me some
of the best things in the collection. Hi
there.
>> Hi. Nice to see you again.
>> Good, thank you. So, you've got some
stuff to show me.
>> I have, yes.
>> Oh, what's this?
>> Let's come over here.
>> The commonplace book.
>> Yeah.
>> Are they great fun?
>> I must say, this is my favorite item in
the archives. Um it was written by the
first Duchess of Marlborough, Sarah.
>> First?
>> And
>> She was a great woman herself.
>> I know, and we don't have much of her
material here.
Uh it's her commonplace book, so it's
it's a journal, and she writes about her
views on
life, love, and the universe, quoting
philosophers, and mentioning her her
opinions in relation to that.
>> And this has never been transcribed and
published?
>> We have got a transcription, but it has
never been formally published, no.
>> That's interesting, cuz she's one of the
preeminent political figures of her
generation. Is that a case of sexism?
Has she been overlooked? Why is that?
>> Could be a It could be a combination of
of those things. It's one of the
fascinating things about uh private
archives.
>> And so she This is the book in This has
not been stuck in. I mean, this is the
book in which she wrote.
>> Yes.
>> there scribbling away.
>> And and scribbling is is probably an
excellent definition of that.
>> glad you're choosing that.
>> [laughter]
>> We do have a a transcription. We can see
the word uh "God" there.
>> God. Do we learn things about the
politics of late Stuart England this or
is this sort of philosophical and and
personal?
>> I think it's a combination of both. I
mean, she discusses her relationship
with family and friends that she'd
fallen out with over the years
indirectly.
Um which which she did, but I think the
way that she phrases it in this book is
she defends herself by saying a true
friend is somebody who cares for you
enough to speak your mind.
Uh and then she will back that up with
philosophical philosophical evidence um
without directing it at a particular
individual.
>> And so this is a This is a treasure. I
mean, this is one of the most famous
people in the early 18th century, and
you've got this gigantic sort of You've
got access to her mind.
>> Yes. Yes, it's an enormous privilege.
>> Right, what's next?
>> Next,
I have a rather lovely item here
that was produced in 1878,
which was an address to the 7th Duchess
of Marlborough, uh Winston Churchill's
grandma. It was uh produced in 1878
uh by the children of the industrial
school in Cork when she spent time in
Ireland with her husband. She was
dedicated to setting up a fund to help
uh poverty through um the the potato and
famine plight. And we've got a
collection of of these beautiful
addresses, which as you can see there's
um so much detail that the the children
and the teachers have worked on as a as
a thank you.
And uh I think it creates quite a lovely
message. The images you're seeing the
children kind of working on the roof and
and but there's you know a little girl
still with a welcome sign and and
there's flowers and it's almost telling
the story how you're working on the
bottom with the thorns that develop
into into flowers at the top. So I think
when they start may it please your grace
then I think I think that she would be
pleased with
>> think of the British aristocracy of
being very popular in Ireland so that's
an interesting
>> Yeah. She she made an enormous
difference and raised a lot of money.
>> What's next?
>> Finally here I've got a 1772
map
of the manner of Woodstock.
>> And that's where we are now is it?
>> Which is where we are now and
this was created by the surveyor Thomas
Pride.
When we have a look inside
>> Oh look how beautiful that is.
Wow.
>> Look at the colors.
>> I love that.
>> And this is the manner of Woodstock is
detailed here which are now sort of
villages.
You've got
the palace here and Coombe, Woodstock
itself, Old Woodstock, Bladon.
But I think it is the the colors are so
vibrant.
>> That's just gorgeous isn't it?
I'm sure the Duke enjoyed looking out on
all his domains.
>> [laughter]
>> Absolutely must be quite satisfying.
>> I mean is it is it stupid to ask how
many sort of objects are in the archive?
>> Actually do you know what? I don't know.
I know that there are 30,000 items
cataloged.
>> 30,000 okay.
>> And I reckon that that's what? 60% of
the archives?
>> And so there's whole boxes of letters
and farm receipts and things that have
just never been cataloged.
>> Yeah really exciting. So as you're
walking around the room we've got a
number of of boxes that are yet to be
explored.
>> That's the dream of all archivists.
>> Exactly. Exactly. It's a new new
adventure every day.
>> So, people go to the palace and look for
all the treasures in there, but the real
treasure is in this room.
>> Absolutely. Yes. Yes, they are.
>> [music]
>> It was wonderful to see that unique book
belonging to Sarah Churchill.
The recent Oscar winning film The
Favourite has made her once again a
public figure.
But, there's one Blenheim resident whose
fame outshines all others.
Blenheim tour guide Peter Gill is going
to tell me his story.
>> Hello. How are you?
>> Hello. Welcome, Dan. I'm Peter.
>> you, Peter.
>> you.
>> You're telling me about the illustrious
man who was born How How come he was
born here?
>> Well, his parents actually lived in
London. He should have been born there,
but he had other ideas. He was a very
impatient man, so his parents were
visiting here in a weekend in November
1874, and he decided to arrive in the
world a few weeks earlier than planned.
So, he later said, "I chose to be born
in Blenheim Palace." I don't think he
had much choice, really.
>> And they They weren't just They weren't
just guests. I mean, they were They were
part of the family, weren't they?
>> Yes, they were. Yes. His grandfather, if
you look at the chart here,
was the 7th Duke of Marlborough, and
they had a number of sons and daughters.
The eldest son, George, became the 8th
Duke on the death of his father, but the
younger son is Randolph Churchill, and
that's the father of Winston. And he
married this American lady from New
York, Jenny Jerome.
So, Winston Churchill is in fact half
American by birth.
>> Half American.
>> Yes.
>> Born in the ancestral home, and that
remained very important to him, didn't
>> It did, indeed. He loved this place and
very much he regarded it as his
ancestral home. It wasn't his actual
home, just the fact that he was born
here, in fact.
>> So, this is his saddle.
>> This is his baby saddle. Yes, I think he
learned to ride his pony, Rob Roy, here
all around the palace grounds, cuz he
spent a lot of his school holidays here.
His parents were rather dysfunctional
really. They didn't come to see him.
They didn't look after him in the
holidays too much. So, he was here with
his grandmother. And he learned to ride
all around Blenheim Palace on Rob Roy,
his pony.
>> And he used to have endless toy
soldiers, endlessly playing battles and
things.
>> Yes, he could have been a military man
quite easily. He could have had his
military career, but he chose to be a
politician, of course.
>> And when he was playing soldiers with
his friends, he was usually in charge?
>> Absolutely, yes. He used to play a game
with his cousin, the ninth duke. And the
the game was sort of fighting the
French, if you like. And he was always
head of the English army. He was the
general. And his cousin was the enemy.
And he always won. That was one of the
rules.
>> [laughter]
>> He was always the the boss, if you like.
It's typical Winston. It's very typical.
>> a little white sailor suit.
>> [laughter]
>> So, then we're going into the room where
Winston Churchill was born on the 30th
of November, 1874. And you'll see here
some examples of his paintings. Look at
them.
>> They're beautiful, aren't they?
>> Yes. He came to Blenheim Palace. He
painted number of paintings inside the
palace, as well as in the gardens.
Again, emphasizing how much he was
influenced by Blenheim Palace, how much
he loved it, regarded it very much as
his
actual ancestral home. And this is the
bed he was born in. And on the end of
the bed, you can see there his curls,
cut off at about the age of four or
five.
So, up to that stage he had long curls
and dressed as a girl, would you
believe? And then he was breeched, which
means he had breeches put on him and
dressed as a boy.
>> Right.
>> Cuz up to that stage they were just
known as children. They weren't sort of
boys and girls. They were children.
>> What a wild you know, she his mother
comes here for a sociable weekend and
she ends up ends up going through labor
and
having this point. And I think
the fact that he was born in this palace
in the in the heart of his ancestral
home, it gave him that sense of it he
thought he was part of something pretty
big. It didn't It didn't come as a
surprise to him he was Prime Minister,
did it? I mean
>> Not really. It's all part of his
destiny, I think. He
He loved it. He loved it. His parents
were actually here for the weekend
attending a ball in the long library.
And so you could see they were rushed up
the corridor and Jenny Jerome, his
mother, was put into bed here and a few
hours later Winston Churchill was born
here. Very proud of that.
>> And is this his actual easel here?
>> lovely painting there and his actual
easel or one of them. He had several of
these. He spent a lot of time painting
here, in France, in Morocco, etc.
>> Astonishing.
>> He's a very accomplished artist.
Exhibiting in the Royal Academy.
Beautiful paintings, some of them.
>> The story began in this room.
That would That would take him
all over the world. I mean, it's just
that he was one of the dominant figures
of the 20th century.
>> He was indeed. He was indeed. And um
never lost the influence of Blenheim
Palace. I think that's most important.
And chose to be buried, of course,
within sight of it. So it just shows how
much this did influence him. But this is
where it all started in 1874 on the 30th
of November.
>> [music]
>> Astonishing chapel here at Blenheim
Palace. We have Winston Churchill's
father here, his grandfather here. And
this is the chapel in which Winston
Churchill was christened as a baby. But
when you're in here, you're left in no
doubt Winston Churchill is but a
footnote. The real
person that you're here to celebrate, to
remember in this room
is the first duke,
John Churchill, Duke of Marlborough.
Even the altar has been shifted to one
side so the people in the pews, the
worshipers,
frankly, worship his monument, his
memorial,
instead of the altar.
There he is with his wife Sarah looking
adoringly up at him.
Uh and his two sons. His daughters don't
get a look in, which is ironic given the
importance of the female line and the
and the women in the in the story of
this dynasty.
And there are scenes from his military
career carved out at the base there. You
are left in no doubt when you visit
Blenheim Palace and when you visit this
chapel that this is a gigantic shrine to
one of the most important military and
political figures
in British history.
>> [music]
>> So, Blenheim is now a unique mixture of
memorial, family home, and national
treasure.
As well
as being the birthplace
of one of the greatest Britons of all
time.
>> [music]
>> Winston Churchill obviously went through
life
carrying Blenheim close to his heart.
And now,
thanks to Winston Churchill, we carry it
in our pocket.
This is the five-pound note. And on it,
we have Winston Churchill, who regularly
tops polls as the most successful,
[music]
respected Briton of all time.
And there, in the corner, just above and
to the right of the great man himself,
is a little reference to Blenheim.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Ever since William the Conqueror came
here almost a thousand years ago,
Windsor, on the banks of the River
Thames,
has been home to a castle.
>> Windsor Castle isn't just one of the
Queen's favorite palaces, it is
absolutely central to the monarchy.
It has been a royal palace for longer
than any other building in Europe. The
story begins around a thousand years
ago. The Normans arrived here. They
conquered England 1066, and they chose
this spot next to a strategic river
crossing over the Thames and dominating
London to the west as a place for a
stronghold. They built this artificial
mound. They put a tower on top of it.
And since then, kings and queens have
enlarged and invested on a gigantic
scale. Edward III turned this [music]
into one of the great royal residences,
spending more money on this than any
other secular project of the time. And
as a result, today
it is magnificent.
>> [music]
>> To get an exclusive tour, I'm meeting
curator Kate Heard.
>> Hello Kate, how are you?
>> Hello. Hello.
>> Thanks for having me in your castle.
Now, we I I always think of Windsor as a
sort of medieval fortress, but actually
it's like a palatial stately home, isn't
it?
>> It It was fortress that. Well, it's a
medieval castle, but the castle you see
today is largely the work of George IV,
who was king from 1820.
>> And and he turned it into a sort of a
modern house.
>> He did. He inherited a castle which had
been changed from the medieval castle in
the 17th century. His parents had made
some changes, and for him it didn't work
as a as a modern royal residence. So, he
set about this huge program of
rebuilding and reconstructing and and
redesigning.
>> This This is beautiful here, isn't it?
>> This is just wonderful. This is his
original entrance hall. So, he opened it
up, so his visitors would come through
that door and would be able to walk into
this magnificent space.
>> feels a little bit to me like a 19th
century Gothic, which we think of being
later in the century, do we?
>> It is absolutely. It's um It was always
the entrance to the castle, but it was a
smaller entrance.
George the third had had a staircase
coming up, but George the fourth opens
it up. But, he's so aware of the
medieval history of the castle, he does
it in that Gothic that Gothic style.
>> So, for people who don't want to talk
about this like kind of fake, really.
>> [laughter]
>> It's re- reimagined Gothic. I mean,
it's fake in a sense, but reimagined.
They were very consciously looking back
to particularly the reign of Edward the
third, who was the another great builder
at the castle.
>> Okay.
>> Creates this amazing vaulting system.
>> It's stunning, isn't it? And yet, and so
I guess visitors come here and think,
"Oh, medieval." In fact, it's only 150
and 200 years old.
>> Absolutely. George the fourth had been
wanting to get his hands on Windsor for
so long, and he really goes to town with
this medieval history when he does.
>> You say that. Is that because Windsor is
in some ways the sort of spiritual core
of the of the English and British
monarchy?
>> It's the medieval fortress. He's very
interested in medieval history. Um it's
it's possibly the most imposing
residence. Remember Buckingham Palace,
which is now really grand, when he
inherited it was quite a small townhouse
his mother had lived in. So, this is the
grandest and most imposing of the royal
residences.
>> And I guess it's the one that's
associated with Edward the third that
all they all loved.
>> Absolutely. Absolutely.
>> Um Charles the second was fond very fond
of it here as well.
>> He'd also lived here as a as a boy. I
mean, remember it's his family home as a
as Prince of Wales. So, he has a great
fondness for the place.
>> So, this is their Are they allowed to
say but is this their sort of premier
residence?
>> I think for George the fourth it is the
one that he is becomes most interested
in. It's the one that he really We know
that he spends hours pouring over the
redesigns. He becomes really occupied by
it. So, I think for him it is the castle
that he castle and the residence that he
spends the most time on.
>> And what about subsequent to that? Well,
what about Victoria, his his niece? What
did she make of it?
>> Well, Queen Victoria inherited it and
she also made great changes to the
castle. So, um the space that we're in,
you can hear it echoing, you can hear
the the size of it. She bricks it off
because she changes the staircase again,
she bricks it off, she doesn't want this
grand entrance. Um and it's only now
that it's been opened up again and we
can appreciate that great vision of of
George IV who wanted his guests to come
up that wonderful approach, the long
walk, and through those through those
doors.
>> Stephanie, why did Victoria brick it
off?
>> Well, I think she just again, it's a
different time, the castle has different
needs. You know, each each generation
needs something different from it.
>> Amazing. Right, where are we off to
next?
>> I think let's go to the state
apartments.
>> Let's do it.
>> [music]
>> This is the grandest staircase I've ever
seen in my life.
>> Isn't it wonderful? It's the entrance to
the state apartments with George IV
looking over it.
>> Looking at all the visitors to his new
rooms?
>> Absolutely, yes.
>> And a huge amount of
weapons, arms, and armor.
>> Yes, all from the royal collection, that
historic collection that goes right the
way back. But George IV is a big
collector of arms and armor as well.
>> Well, he was obsessed with the military,
wasn't he?
>> Absolutely, everything he can do. He's
not allowed to fight, but he forms this
incredible collection.
>> And even more muskets and swords here?
>> Absolutely, this in the medieval castle
this space would have formed a a guard
chamber. It would have protected the
state apartments, so that this display
reflects that function.
>> And
I'm trying to think, Windsor Castle, I
think it was threatened when
during the sort of civil war at King
John when Prince Louis came over. I I
can't Was it besieged at the time?
>> I No no other sieges as it were. Henry
VIII I know during the Pilgrimage of
Grace was here and there was a worry
that it would be besieged, but it it
It wasn't.
>> So now, which which are these rooms?
Just what is this?
>> Isn't it stunning?
>> Wow.
>> This is the Waterloo Chamber, which
um holds this incredible series of
portraits largely by Sir Thomas Lawrence
of the men who were responsible for the
defeat of Napoleon in the early 19th
century.
>> We got Wellington up there.
>> Absolutely.
>> Commander at Waterloo, Blücher, his key
ally at Waterloo.
>> Yeah.
>> Wow.
>> It's It's It's an incredible series of
portraits.
>> Emperor of Austria.
>> Yes.
>> So George IV is very kind to let his dad
go above the mantelpiece.
>> George III is the monarch who was ruling
the country. So at that point, our
George is Prince Regent, so he
acknowledges his father's his father's
role, but he he puts himself in in very
clear second place.
>> I love this cuz this is basically all
the crowned heads and the leading
aristocratic military men of Europe, all
who for whom Napoleon represented an
existential threat. So this is a giant
celebration.
>> Absolutely. Yes. And this commission
starts before the Battle of Waterloo. It
dates from 1814 when they thought that
Napoleon had been defeated and and
George sends Thomas Lawrence out to make
these incredible paintings. And the the
half-lengths of the statesmen as well,
he's acknowledging the role of of
statesmanship in that creating that
peace after Waterloo, after the fall of
Napoleon.
>> Was this room always a a sort of
banqueting hall?
>> No, in the medieval castle, you're
standing in the open air. So you're in
one of of Edward III's courtyards in the
middle of a run of apartments.
And George IV had commissioned these
incredible paintings. He wants a
Waterloo Gallery,
and this space is earmarked for it, but
it's not really finished until after his
death. So it's roofed over and then
these wonderful lights are added. Um
it's not really finished until the reign
of Queen Victoria.
>> How funny. I I always think of a very
modern idea which you take your big
atrium, your big courtyards and turn
them into an atrium, but actually they
were doing it in the 19th century.
>> Absolutely. It's a It's a wonderful use
of the space. And the space also looks
back to the earlier castle, to the
17th century castle. You can see these
wonderful pieces of wood carving. And
they're taken from Charles II's Chapel
there by Grinling Gibbons, reused in
this space, and they work wonderfully
here.
>> Wow.
>> This is St. George's Hall, which is
>> Fantastic, and has always had the
function of a a great hall um for for
meetings, for feastings,
for great occasions.
>> And this was a medieval hall?
>> Originally, this space was Edward III's.
Um we still have Edward III's undercroft
beneath, um which is just recently
opened up for the first time.
It becomes under Charles II a very
baroque space. It looks very different
with wall paintings.
Um under George IV, it's turned again
into a a medieval-looking space, a
Gothic space, and he lengthens the hall
by essentially knocking the chapel and
the hall together.
But it's not entirely successful. His
His ceiling His Gothic ceiling is quite
low, and everything is plaster,
essentially a plaster fake for a
medieval building.
Now, the 1992 fire affected this space
very badly. So, what you see again is
the reconstruction in 1992
um of this great sort of Gothic space.
This amazing hammerbeam ceiling roof um
designed by James Downs. It's in green
oak. It's a It's a a masterpiece of of
craftsmanship, which the hall has always
been, all that way back.
>> It's amazing. It's so Something so
British about this that it's a
it's a reconstruction of a reimagining
of a And yet, so it's both very historic
and and and very long, but also
ever-changing.
>> Ever-changing, but always grounded in
history, and the
it reflects the importance of the castle
as the seat of the Order of the Garter,
which is the oldest order of chivalry,
founded again by Edward III in 1348.
And so the shields you can see
decorating the space are the shields of
the Knights of the Garter all the way
back.
>> Really?
>> Yes.
>> That's remarkable continuity, isn't it?
>> It's stunning.
>> A lot of arms and armor on the walls
again. I'm noticing a theme here.
>> Yes.
>> And what's that up That's a very fine
one up there.
>> That's wonderful. That is the champion's
armor, which was last used at the
coronation of George IV.
>> What's that?
>> That is um traditionally, going all the
way back to the Middle Ages, um a
champion defends the king's honor after
he's been crowned, and issues a
challenge to anyone who may want to
challenge the new king, and throws down
his gauntlet. And that is the armor
that's worn by the champion. It's a It's
a hereditary office.
>> Really?
>> Yes.
>> Whoever that was, and his father and his
grandfather would ride through the
coronation.
>> It's the Dymoke family, absolutely. And
George IV is the last person to have had
the champion appear at his coronation.
>> But
And so what he what he rides a horse
through the party, and throws down the
gauntlet.
>> indeed. Through the coronation banquet
for George IV in Westminster Hall,
the the horse rides in as part of the
part of the ceremony.
>> What happens if, you know, grandson
Dymoke was a bit of a softy?
>> [laughter]
>> He still gets to do it.
>> And they have still have functions in
here?
>> Still used as a space that is for for
feasting, for state occasions. It's
still used in the way that Edward III
would have been familiar with.
>> And there's as we leave, there's George
IV.
>> There's our George again, yes.
>> Looking down on what he's built.
It's a nice little room, isn't it?
>> Isn't it fantastic? That octagon,
looking back again to the medieval
precedent, places like Ely Cathedral
with the the octagon there.
>> And
>> This is
>> Who's this? This Is this Henry VIII?
>> This is Henry VIII, yes.
>> it. That's so cool.
>> You get that sense of the figure, don't
you? Really imposing presence.
Uh just amazing.
>> They must have had to let that out
slightly, I see.
>> Yes. Well, I think it was probably yeah,
made for him in his mature years.
>> And then we've got all the silver and
the
>> Some of that wonderful yeah,
silver and gilt from the royal
collection. Really stunning pieces.
>> this just accumulated over hundreds of
years.
>> Absolutely. Just added to by each
generation.
>> It's amazing.
That's unique the the continuity of the
of the
British state and the and its and its
royal tradition. Means that you must
just have centuries and centuries of all
this these treasures.
>> Absolutely. Yes, all all each each
monarch is also aware of the history.
So, you get George the fourth looking
back to the Middle Ages and looking back
to the Baroque period and building on
that when he's building his own
collection. So, you get those that that
awareness of the layers too.
>> Where next?
>> This way.
>> [music]
>> So, this is the really wonderful crimson
drawing room.
>> Wow. This is the This is pure George the
fourth. It's just so opulent and
gorgeous, isn't it?
>> It is. It was one of his private
apartments. It's one of his one of his
his major reception room. So, he would
have private guests here, but it's it's
one of his
>> So, you think we're getting close to his
tastes and his
>> I think we're right in the middle of his
taste here. It's very different from the
rest of the castle. It's it's in this
French neoclassical taste that he loved
all his life. It's it's a it's a
stunning space.
>> And it's this French neo
these objects that he purchased are now
so famous at Buckingham Palace and
everywhere else because he just hoovered
this stuff up, didn't he?
>> Absolutely. I mean, all this wonderful
furniture was commissioned by him to
furnish obviously he's he's got a small
residence as prince and then he gains
Buckingham Palace, he gains Windsor
Castle, he needs all this furniture to
to to to to to fill it up. So, he
commissions these wonderful suites of
furniture. Just stunning.
>> love the gilded detail on the doors.
>> Some of the gilding on the doors was
brought from Carlton House again. and so
he brings quite a bit of material from
Carlton House. The fireplaces actually
dates from 1807 before this room was
established and is is from Carlton House
and was brought here when Carlton House,
his London residence, was demolished.
>> And
this is room um survive the Great Fire
in the 19
>> No, very sadly this room was very badly
damaged, but it was reconstructed
using the original documents from George
IV's reign. And when George IV is
planning this room, set of really
magnificent watercolors are made for him
to show what the room might look like,
and that archive he uses in planning his
spaces is then reused in the 1990s for
planning this space and it it's
beautiful. He would have felt very at
home in this room even though it is
largely reconstructed.
>> So in the
center of this
>> Mhm.
>> gigantic royal palace
>> administrative headquarters, medieval
with you think this is kind of George
IV's
personal space?
>> this is where we we meet him most of
all. His his the place where he would
have relaxed. He would have He's got his
portraits of his sisters on the wall. I
think he, you know, he would have
enjoyed this space.
>> And he had a He was a sad man in many
ways. He was extraordinarily infirm with
a variety of illnesses towards the end
of his life.
>> strange to think of him sitting here in
those declining years when he was almost
a recluse, wasn't he?
>> He was a recluse. He didn't like people
looking at him. He was he he'd been
tortured by satirists. He'd been he he
really did withdraw during during his
reign, that 10-year reign. But he
surrounded himself with these incredible
objects he'd collected and he clearly
takes such pleasure in craftsmanship and
beauty and this beautiful sort of skill
in creating things in textures and
colors. So
you can imagine him very happy in these
rooms.
>> Isn't it funny that he probably felt
insecure because compared to say George
II or the Duke of Cumberland, you know,
his martial relatives
>> Yes.
>> he he he he he never fought on the
battlefield.
>> Yes.
>> he
>> actually
what the modern world looks for now is a
collector and interior designer. So, his
reputation's probably higher than ever.
>> We can appreciate him now for these
amazing things he left us, [music] this
incredible collection he formed.
>> [music]